A Guide to the Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation Director's Correspondence and Subject Files, 1999-2013
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation, 1999-2013
The Library of Virginia
44251, 51734
6 cu. ft.
Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 44251 transferred 13 April 2009.
Accession 51734 transferred 11 February 2016.
Historical Information
The Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation (DRPT) was initially a section of the Virginia Dept. of Transportation. In 1992, the DRPT was established as a separate agency responsible for rail and public transportation services. The Department reports to the Secretary of Transportation, but also continues to work closely with the Dept. of Transportation. The DRPT focuses on the movement of people and goods throughout the Commonwealth by concentrating on railroads, public transportation and commuter services. The mission of the DRPT is to improve the mobility of people and goods while expanding transportation choices in Virginia.
The Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation supports passenger and freight rail initiatives through advocacy, funding, providing advice, and conducting research. To safeguard Virginia's interests in the national rail network, the Department also represents the Commonwealth's interests regarding national rail issues. The Department also partners with, advises, supports and funds public transportation programs statewide, such as bus systems and commuter service organizations.
Scope and Content
Contains correspondence and subject files from the Director of the Virginia Department of Rail and Public Transportation that document the planning, direction, and implementation of agency programs and are evidence of actions and policy decisions.
Accession 44251 includes subject files that are mostly related to the Dulles Toll Road project, and the correspondence is almost entirely consituent. The correspondence comes from both the agency head, Matthew Tucker and the Secretary of Transportation, Pierce Homer. Earlier correspondence from agency head Karen Rae is also available.
Accession 51734 includes Director Thelma Drake’s subject files and constituent correspondence, 2006-2013, as well as some files from previous Director Matthew Tucker.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Director's Correspondence and Subject Files, 1999-2013
Contents List
- Series I. Director's Correspondence and Subject Files, 1999-2013.
  - Accession 44251 (1999-2008).
    - Dulles, 2008. (Box 1)
    - Dulles, 2002-2003. (Box 1)
    - Dulles/Gov., 2004. (Box 1)
    - Dulles, 2003-2004. (Box 1)
    - Dulles MWAA Negotiations, 2006-2007. (Box 1)
    - Dulles ROD, 2004-2005. (Box 1)
    - PPTA Negotiations, 2002-2004. (Box 1)
    - Project Director, 2003. (Box 1)
    - Loose Dulles Documents, 2004-2007. (Box 1)
    - Dulles, 2007-2008. (Box 1)
    - Dulles, 2008. (Box 1)
    - Gray V. Virginia Secretary of Transportation, Dulles Toll Opinion, 2008. (Box 1)
    - Gray v. Virginia Secretary of Transportation, Dulles Road Transfer Case, 2007-2008. (Box 1)
    - Dulles Large Bore Tunnel Study, 2007. (Box 1)
    - Dulles SAF and SEC Management Plan, 2006. (Box 1)
    - Dulles Toll Road Agreement, Original, 2007. (Box 1)
    - Constituent Correspondence (Loose / Unlabeled Folders), 2007. (Box 2)
    - Letters for Secretary's Signature, 2006. (Box 2)
    - Matthew O. Tucker, Letters of Response (Binder), 2006. (Box 2)
    - Matt's Letters of Response, 2007-2008. (Box 2)
    - Matt's Signature, 2007. (Box 2)
    - General Correspondence, 2003-2004. (Box 2)
    - FOIA Request, 2003. (Box 2)
    - Karen Rae Correspondence, 1999-2004. (Box 2)
    - Photographs, undated. (Box 2)
    - Agency Head Correspondence and Email (Loose), 2007-2008. (Box 3)
    - Secretary of Transportation Correspondence and Email (Loose), 2007-2008. (Box 3)
  - Accession 51734 (2006-2013).
    - 511 Virginia. (Box 1)
    - Abusive driver fees. (Box 1)
    - American Public Transportation Association (APTA). (Box 1)
    - American Road and Transportation Builders Association (ARTBA). (Box 1)
    - Attorney General. (Box 1 and 2)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts. (Box 1)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts (APA) audits. (Box 1)
    - Auditor of Public Accounts (APA) reports. (Box 1)
    - Base Closure and Realignment Commission (BRAC). (Box 1)
    - Budget. (Box 1)
    - Captital Beltway. (Box 1)
    - Commonwealth Transportation Board (CTB). (Box 1)
    - Commuter Connections. (Box 1)
    - Commuter Train Service. (Box 1)
    - Congress - Public Law 104-88. (Box 1)
    - Continuity of Operations Plan (COOP). (Box 1)
    - Craney Island Connection. (Box 1)
    - Dulles transfer. (Box 1)
    - Energy Efficiency in state government. (Box 1)
    - Ethics/Code of Conduct. (Box 1)
    - Fairfax County. (Box 1)
    - Federal HR 40. (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Certification/Assurances. (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Correspondence. (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Memorandum of Understanding (MOU). (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Public Private Partnership (PPP) comment. (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Regional. (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Section 5317. (Box 1)
    - Federal Transit Administration (FTA) - Statewide Transportation Improvement Plan (STIP). (Box 1)
    - Finance - Asset Management. (Box 1)
    - Finance - SWAM report. (Box 1)
    - Fredericksburg Area Metropolitan Planning Organization (FAMPO). (Box 1)
    - Foley invoices. (Box 1)
    - General Assembly - Protocols. (Box 1)
    - General Assembly 2007. (Box 1)
    - General Assembly 2007 - HB 3202. (Box 1)
    - Google. (Box 1)
    - Governor. (Box 1)
    - Governor - 2006 Briefing. (Box 1)
    - Governor - 2008 Briefing. (Box 1)
    - Governor - Executive Orders. (Box 1 and 2)
    - Governor - Guidelines for meeting with Corporate Dignitaries. (Box 1)
    - Governor Kaine - 2007 Budget. (Box 1)
    - Governor's Transportation Plan. (Box 1)
    - Greater Richmond Transit Company (GRTC). (Box 1)
    - Greenhouse Gas Reduction. (Box 1)
    - Hampton Roads Planning District Commission (HRPDC). (Box 1)
    - Highway Spending and Funding. (Box 1)
    - Highway Trust Fund. (Box 1)
    - Human Resources. (Box 1)
    - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC) - 2007 State Spending. (Box 1)
    - Matt Tucker presentations. (Box 2)
    - Matthews County - Main Street drainage. (Box 1)
    - Metropolitan Area Transportation Operation Coordination (MATOC). (Box 1)
    - Metropolitan Planning Organization (MPO) (Box 1)
    - Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (MWAA) - Payment of Expenditures Agreement. (Box 1)
    - National Environmental Policy Act. (Box 1)
    - National Environmental Policy Act of 1969. (Box 1)
    - National Governors Association (NGA) - Transportation Funding. (Box 2)
    - National Incident Management System (NIMS). (Box 1)
    - National Surface Transportation Board (NSTB). (Box 1)
    - News articles. (Box 1)
    - Northeast Corridor Action Plan. (Box 1)
    - Northeast Corridor - East Corridor. (Box 1)
    - Northern Virginia (NOVA) - Funding. (Box 1)
    - Northern Virginia (NOVA) - Transit tour. (Box 1)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Authority (NVTA). (Box 2)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Authority (NVTA) - Battlefield Parkway. (Box 2)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Authority (NVTA) - Bond Validation Suit. (Box 2)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Authority (NVTA) - Correspondence. (Box 2)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Commission (NVTC) (Box 2)
    - Petroleum savings. (Box 2)
    - Pierce (2006). (Box 2)
    - Protocol U.S. Congress. (Box 2)
    - Public Private Partnerships. (Box 2)
    - Public Private Transportation Act of 1995. (Box 2)
    - Public Transit - Winchester. (Box 2)
    - Public Transportation - Greater Richmond Transit Company (GRTC). (Box 2)
    - Public Transportation - Potomac and Rappahannock Transportation Commission (PRTC) (Box 2)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Dashboard. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Designee letter. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Early Action. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Grants. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Memorandum of Understanding (MOU). (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Policy. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - SSO. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Subpoena. (Box 1)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of (DRPT) - Tier Funding Proposal FY2008 (Box 2)
    - Rail transfer. (Box 1)
    - Regional Transit - Charlottesville. (Box 2)
    - Restricted Structure Atlas. (Box 2)
    - Richmond Regional Planning District - Memorandum of Understanding (MOU). (Box 1)
    - Rt. 1. (Box 2)
    - Rt. 29. (Box 2)
    - Rt. 460. (Box 2)
    - Secretary of Transportation. (Box 2)
    - Secretary of Transportation - Legislative Brief (2008) (Box 2)
    - Secretary of Transportation - Legislative Studies. (Box 2)
    - Southside Virginia Training Center (SVTC) - Memorandum of Understanding (MOU). (Box 1)
    - State car information. (Box 2)
    - Statewide Transporation Improvement Plan (STIP). (Box 2)
    - Suffolk City - Resolution for Commonwealth Railway. (Box 2)
    - Surface Transportation Board (STP). (Box 2)
    - Telework. (Box 2)
    - TransDominion Express (TDX). (Box 2)
    - Transit Authority. (Box 2)
    - Transit Funding. (Box 2)
    - Transit Miscellaneous. (Box 2)
    - Transit Projects. (Box 2)
    - Transit Work Group. (Box 2)
    - Transportation - Articles/Publications. (Box 2)
    - Transportation Accountability Commission. (Box 2)
    - Transportation Enhancement Program. (Box 2)
    - Transportation Partnership Opportunity Fund. (Box 2)
    - Transportation Performance Report (2006). (Box 2)
    - Transportation Summit - Fairfax. (Box 2)
    - Uniform Certification Program (UCP) Agreement - USDOT. (Box 2)
    - United States Dept. of Transportation (USDOT) - Federal Transit Administration (FTA). (Box 1)
    - United We Ride. (Box 2)
    - Universal Access to Paratransit Riders. (Box 2)
    - Urban Partnerships. (Box 2)
    - Virginia Comprehensive Cross Governmental Strategic Plan (2006). (Box 2)
    - Virginia Dept. of Transportation (VDOT) - Access Management. (Box 2)
    - Virginia Dept. of Transportation (VDOT) - General. (Box 2)
    - Virginia Dept. of Transportation (VDOT) - Hot Lanes. (Box 2)
    - Virginia Transportation Conference - Roanoke (2006). (Box 2)